Harry S. Wender 009
People's Archive, MLK Library
Harry S. Wender Papers
1930-1973
People's Archive, MLK Library
Wender, Harry S.
009
1 Linear feet
2 Boxes
Arrangement
Papers processed without series.
Biographical / Historical
Harry S. Wender was born in 1908 in Knoxville, Tennessee and moved to Washington, D.C. as an infant. He graduated from Smallwood-Bowen School in 1921, Central High School in 1925, and Georgetown Law School in 1933. From 1925-1927 Mr. Wender attended pre-legal coursework at George Washington University. Mr. Wender was a practicing attorney in Washington, D.C. from 1932 until his death; focusing his work on racial segregation in D.C. recreation facilities, traffic law, transportation issues, and automobile insurance law. On October 14, 1937 Mr. Wender married Gerturude Schwarz. He was a member of B'Nai Brith, Southwest Citizens' Association, Federation of Citizens' Associations, D.C. Suffrage Association, Commissioners' Traffic Advisory Council, Washington Hebrew Congregation, District of Columbia and American Bar Associations, Association of Plaintiff's Trial Attorneys of Metropolitan Washington, Jewish Historical Society of Greater Washington, and editor of D. C. Bar Journal. He served as chairman of the D.C. Recreation Board from 1942-1952 and President of the Southwest Citizens' Association. Mr. Wender received awards for Outstanding Trial Lawyer of the Year Award from D.C. Association of Plaintiff's Trial Attorneys; Certificate of Merit from D.C. Commissioners; and October 4, 1983 was designated by Mayor Marion Barry as "Harry Wender Day." Mr. Wender died December 14, 1985.
Custodial History
Donor unknown.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, internal memorandum, proposals, publicity materials, legislative materials, meeting minutes, editorials, and membership lists. Most of these materials are related to Home Rule voting rights for D.C. residents from the 1930s through the 1960s. Organizations mentioned in this collection include the D.C. Suffrage Association, Committee of the 100, Citizens Conference on District Suffrage, and Young People's Home Rule League.
Neighborhoods; Home rule -- Washington (D.C.); Suffrage; Lobbying
- Series 1
  - Correspondence, 1930-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Proposals for Home Rule, 1930-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - National Support for Home Rule, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - D.C. Home Rule Committee, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Home Rule Committee budgets, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Actions of the D.C. Suffrage Association, 1930-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Local Support for Home Rule (organization), Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Norman Jay Show Very Truly Yours with Discussion of D.C. suffrage, Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lobbying efforts with Congress, 1939-1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Publicity materials and editorials, 1930-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bills and Reports on the District of Columbia, 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)